Jalil Ogunniyi

\(+(234) 809 948 0333

in linkedin.com/in/jaliloa

Senior full-stack software engineer with 6+ years of experience building and scaling web applications, specializing in Ruby on Rails, React.js, PostgreSQL. Experienced independently managing projects from ideation through to production. Experienced leading teams to build and maintain high throughput systems - armed with lots of technical war stories.

EXPERIENCE

Aster BI (Bookkeeping)

Remote

Co-founder | Full-Stack Software Engineer

Jan 2024 - Present

- Built and launched a bookkeeping product, www.asterbi.com, from scratch using React.js (Hooks, context API, Next.js) and Ruby on Rails.
- Led product direction, conducting 40+ customer clarity calls, defining requirements and executing implementation.
- Scaled to 800+ customers, independently managed product development to deliver 5+ key financial tools, including automated VAT and WHT forms, on-demand financial statements.
- Processed 4,000+ invoices in the first year, along with support for expense tracking, business reports, taxes, and role-based access control.
- Designed and implemented a robust payment processing system capable of 100k daily payments, supporting retries, fallbacks, fees, settlements, and reconciliation. Facilitated API integrations with 2 payment partners.
- Integrated real-time monitoring tools and self-hosted Metabase dashboards for tracking 30+ key performance metrics.
- Built a subscription management system with feature-based plans, trial periods, renewals and prorated payments.

Branch International (Lending & Payments)

Remote

Senior Software Engineer Software Engineer

Oct 2021 - Dec 2023 Apr 2019 - Oct 2021

- Led team of 5 to develop and launch debit cards, handling \$80k in weekly transactions. Built the card application Android UI (Kotlin), and admin tools (Ruby on Rails) for card production, delivery, disputes, and reconciliation.
- Integrated NIBSS payments into Ruby on Rails monolith, saving \$40k/week in bank transfer fees.
- Built a server driven-ui system across Ruby on Rails and Android, enabling optimizations in onboarding and payment flows for all product teams.
- Established app monitoring best practices, reducing crash/ANR by 45% over 12 weeks and boosting play store rankings.
- Led technical team of 7 to build and maintain a wallet system handling 100k+ weekly transactions across Nigeria and Kenya; increasing monthly active users by 25% in the first 12 weeks.
- Integrated GTBank payments using Ruby on Rails, processing \$70k/week in cash payments, supporting loan financing strategy.

Andela (Talent)

Software Engineer

Oct 2018 - April 2021

Hybrid, Lagos

- Enhanced a talent management app(Ruby on Rails/Javascript) with surveys and interactive tutorials increasing NPS from 5 to 6 in 12 weeks.
- Mentored 8 junior engineers in technical and product development skills through the Stackup program.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Technologies & Frameworks

Rails, React.js, Sidekiq, Next.js, Android

Languages

Ruby, Javascript, Typescript, Kotlin

Datastores

PostgreSQL, Redis, SQLite, Snowflake

Devops & Cloud

Heroku, AWS(EC2, S3, RDS, Lambda), Docker, GitHub Actions, CircleCl

Monitoring & Analytics

Datadog, New Relic, Metabase, Sisense, Google Analytics

Other skills & Tools

REST API Integration & Design, Testing, Performance, System Design

PROJECTS

- Active Record ObscuredID (Ruby) Open source(400+ downloads) library for generating exposable IDs for Rails models.
- Paystack Gateway (Ruby) Open source(300+ downloads) library providing modules binding to the official paystack API.

EDUCATION